Guide to the KVOS Channel 12 Film Records 1961-1967
Western Washington University, Heritage Resources
KVOS Channel 12 Film Records
1961-1967
Western Washington University Heritage Resources Center for Pacific Northwest Studies Goltz-Murray Building 808 25th St Bellingham, WA 98225-9123 Phone: 360 650 7747 Email: heritage.resources@wwu.edu http://library.wwu.edu/heritageresources
XOE_CPNWS0030kvos
KVOS Channel 12
18 Linear Ft.
The KVOS Channel 12 Film records comprise reel-to-reel films of KVOS television programs filmed and broadcast between 1961 and 1967. The collection includes copies of the Webster Reports (a monthly program focusing on human interest stories featuring Vancouver, B.C. newsman, Jack Webster) and Channel 12 Specials. Channel 12 Specials comprise interviews and documentaries about significant events and issues in Washington State and British Columbia during the 1960s, including the Seattle World's Fair in 1962, the 1964 Alaskan Earthquake, and issues affecting local public schools and colleges. All collection materials are in 16mm film format.
In 1953 the Federal Communications Commission issued a license for television station KVOS-TV to operate in Bellingham, Washington. Owned by local businessman and entrepreneur Rogan Jones - then the owner of KVOS radio - KVOS-TV broadcast its first program on May 23, 1953, featuring the coronation of British monarch Queen Elizabeth II.
Despite Jones' conviction that television could succeed in a city as small as Bellingham, the station had early difficulties supporting itself. In 1955, Jones responded by establishing an advertising company, KVOS-TV (B.C.) Limited, in Vancouver, British Columbia. The company produced revenue by selling advertising and producing commercials for Canadian businesses. KVOS-TV continued to broadcast from Bellingham, with much of its audience based in British Columbia's Lower Mainland and Vancouver Island.
In 1962 Rogan Jones sold KVOS-TV to the WOMETCO Corporation. KVOS-TV is owned currently by Clear Channel International's entertainment and media group. Rogan Jones' former radio stations currently operate under the call letters of KGMI and KISM but are no longer affiliated with KVOS Television.
The KVOS Channel 12 Film Records comprise select reel-to-reel footage from KVOS television programs The Webster Reports and Channel 12 Specials, broadcast between 1961-1967. A monthly show hosted by Vancouver, B.C. newsman Jack Webster, The Webster Reports programs combine human interest stories with more serious reporting about regional news and events in British Columbia. Channel 12 Specials contain interviews and documentaries, many pertaining to current affairs and local issues in Washington State.
The Webster Reports include "Century 21" (1962), regarding the Seattle World's Fair, as well as programs "A Case of Terror" (1962) and "Road to Nowhere" (1963), about the activities of the Doukhobor sect, The Sons of Freedom, in British Columbia. "The Eye of the Storm" (1963 focuses on the B.C. Prison hostage crisis, in which Webster was both a negotiator and hostage. The Webster Reports also contain a 1963 profile of Christian evangelist and fundamentalist Billy James Hargis.
Channel 12 Specials include a feature on the Seattle World's Fair entitled "Girls, Glitter and Gracie" (1962), footage of the 1964 Alaska Earthquake and programs about issues affecting local public schools and colleges in Bellingham, Washington. "The Color of Black" (1965), features an interview with James Leonard Farmer, Jr, founder and head of the Congress of Racial Equality (CORE). Many of the Channel 12 Specials programs were broadcast live and later taped to video. Most were produced by Al Swift, U.S. Congressman and former News Director of KVOS. The majority were recorded in black and white, with a few later episodes in color.
All reels in the KVOS Channel 12 Film records are 16mm film format. KVOS's original organizational numbering system is reflected in the description of each reel in the collection inventory. Researchers should note that the collection does not contain any supporting or textual documentation regarding the programs or film footage. The Rogan Jones Papers at the Center for Pacific Northwest Studies contain additional information about KVOS television.
The KVOS Channel 12 Film Records are organized in accordance with the following series arrangement:
Series I - Webster Reports, 1961-1966
Series II - Channel 12 Specials, 1962-1967
The Center for Pacific Northwest Studies requires advance arrangements for access to reel-to-reel tapes in the KVOS Channel 12 Film Records.
The reel-to-reel films were donated to the Center for Pacific Northwest Studies by KVOS Television's Department of News and Public Affairs in May of 1977.
The Rogan Jones Papers at the Center for Pacific Northwest Studies contain textual information about KVOS Television as well as supporting documentation for the programs.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
KVOS-TV (Television station: Bellingham, Wash.) --Archives.; Sons of Freedom Dukhobors.
Farmer, James, (1920- )
Television stations--Washington (State)--Bellingham--History--Sources.; Broadcasting--Washington (State)--Bellingham--History--Sources.; Broadcasting--British Columbia--Lower Mainland--History--Sources.; Century 21 Exposition -- (1962: Seattle, Wash.) --History--Sources.; Earthquakes--Alaska--History--Sources.; Universities and colleges--Washington (State)--Bellingham--History--Sources.; Public schools--Washington (State)--Bellingham--History--Sources.; Hargis, Billy James, d 1925-; Burr, Raymond, d 1917-; Berton, Pierre, d 1920-; Horn, Kahn-Tineta; Ford, Leighton; Magnuson, Warren Grant, d 1905-; Mowat, Farley; Connelly, Marc, d 1890-; Avital, Benad; Douglas, William O. (William Orville), d 1898-; Bond, Julian, d 1940-; Gregory, Dick; Treacher, Arthur, d 1894-1975; Swift, Al, d 1935-; Webster, Jack; Farmer, James, d 1920-
Alaska; Washington (State); Moving Images; Journalism; African Americans; Colleges and Universities; Environmental Conditions; Performing Arts; Native Americans; Religion
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Webster Reports, 1961-1966; Series I
  - W-1 The Operators, 1961 December 21 (Box-reel 1/1)
    Length: 30 minutes
    Film Quality (Original): good
    Duplicate: VHS, DVD
    Sound: yes.
    Description: Jack Webster discusses several confidence rackets affecting both Washington and British Columbia, including such petty crime as telephone scams, home repair scams, and predatory magazine subscription schemes. He interviews three former criminal participants: Ed Sokolosky about a chimney repair racket, “Cynthia from Vancouver” about magazine subscription sales techniques, and “Joy” about the living conditions of traveling magazine subscription salesgirls. This reel also includes short commercial advertisements for Purex Bathroom Tissues, CBS Reports, and Black Label Beer.
  - W-2 Pension for a Hero, 1962 January 30 (Box-reel 1/2)
    Length: 32 minutes
    Sound: yes (except last 3 minutes)
    Description: Jack Webster tackles the issue of workman’s compensation in British Columbia, with references to the Compensation Act, and the Mine, Mill, and Smelter’s Union of British Columbia. Three case histories of miners who suffered labor-related injuries are presented. The first is that of John Luka (Luca?), who has a broken back and paralyzed legs from an employment-related rockslide. The second is that of John Anderburg, who is suffering from silicosis and pleurisy resulting from the inhalation of silica dust while on the job. His wife Irene is interviewed about the difficulties of caring for him on his small pension. The third is that of Henry Roueau who lost part of his foot. Last three minutes of the reel consist of supplementary footage of Irene Anderburg at home caring for her husband
  - W-3 Century 21 (Seattle World's Fair), 1962 February 8 (Box-reel 2/1)
    Length: 11 minutes
    Film Quality (Original): spliced scraps of footage; fragmentary.
    Duplicate: DVD, VHS, digital
    Sound: yes (except first 30 seconds)
    Description: Short interviews with director of the 1962 Seattle World’s Fair Gayway about prices and attractions, and Space Needle manager Hoge Sullivan about the Space Needle construction schedule and Space Needle statistics. There is also footage of construction crews at work high atop the almost completed Space Needle.
  - W-4 A Case of Terror, 1962 April 5 (Box-reel 2/2)
    Length: 23 minutes
    Film Quality (Original): Footage is of mixed quality and is spliced from scraps; interviews are fragmentary.
    Duplicate: DVD, VHS
    Sound: partial
    Description: Jack Webster reports on the Doukhobor group “The Sons of Freedom.” The Sons of Freedom were the activist wing of the Doukhobors, a religious Russian immigrant community in the Kootenays region of British Columbia, and were accused of terrorism, vandalism, and other crimes. The pacifist Doukhobors settled in Canada in the 19th century under a treaty which included provisions protecting their pacifism (i.e., exemption from military service and the draft), and their right to educate their children separately. Reel includes portions of interviews with law enforcement and government officials. Footage of a Doukhobor community, and police roadblocks stopping and searching vehicles. For more Doukhobor footage, see W-5, W-15, and W-26.
  - W-5 Maria, Fanny, and Podivinikoff (outtakes from 'A Case of Terror'), 1962 April 5 (Box-reel 2/3)
    Length: 13 minutes
    Film Quality (Original): scraps of footage; fragmentary, incomplete.
    Description: Portions of interviews with three members of the Doukhobor community. The Doukhobors were a group of religious Russian immigrants, and the “Sons of Freedom” sect had been accused of terrorism at the time. Topics include recent arrests of Doukhobor members, possibility of emigration from Canada, freedom of education, culpability for financial losses resulting from destructive protests, and the chosen simplicity of the Doukhobor way of life. For more Doukhobor footage, see W-4, W-15, and W-26.
  - W-6 Yanks and Canadian Labor, 1962 April 26 (Box-reel 3/1)
    Length: 28 minutes
    Description: Jack Webster interviews three union officials during the 1962 Canadian Labor Congress. The topic is the degree to which Canadian union members are beholden to U.S. laws, policies, and direction in international unions with U.S. headquarters (AFL CIO). While all three guests defend Canadian union autonomy and minimize the extent of U.S. dominance, Webster strongly asserts that other Canadian union officials, who refused to appear on the show, make the opposite claim.
  - W-7 Jacks or Better, 1962 October 10 (Box-reel 3/2)
    Film Quality (Original): poor
    Sound: yes (except bad patches)
    Description: An expose of crooked gambling practices and related crime involving card games and dice. Guest for entire episode is Sidney Radner, an expert on card cheating techniques, and author of several books on the subject. Radner demonstrates, in detail, several common sleight-of-hand methods employed by criminals and gamblers in playing, shuffling, and dealing cards for poker and gin-rummy. He also explains the use of marked cards and loaded dice. Original film features several short bad patches of 1-5 seconds, in which the image, sound, or both are garbled. On the DVD the first 23 seconds are a bad patch. Film requires extensive splicing due to numerous breaks.
  - W-9 Where is David Loveday?, 1963 January 2 (Box-reel 3/3)
    Sound: yes
    Description: Webster explores the case of Vancouver, B.C. teenager David Loveday, who ran away from home at the age of 13 and is still missing two and a half years later. His mother and stepfather are interviewed at length. Detective Smith of the Vancouver Police is also interviewed about missing children and teenage runaways in Vancouver and British Columbia. Note: film begins after 30 seconds on DVD
  - W-10 The Eye of the Storm, 1963 April 24 (Box-reel 4/1)
    Length: 26 minutes
    Description: Webster discusses the 1963 prisoner takeover of the British Columbia Penitentiary, with an emphasis on his own involvement as a negotiator and, at one point, a hostage. Webster offers an hour by hour account of the prison riot, which began as a reaction to poor conditions. Webster demonstrates how prisoners fashioned homemade weapons, including makeshift knives and Molotov cocktails made from light bulbs and gasoline. Film also includes excerpts of interviews with several prison and law enforcement officials, aerial footage of the prison during the uprising, footage of the destruction and carnage inside the prison, and footage of Mounties, national guardsmen, squad cars, and police surrounding the prison.
  - W-11 North Pacific Salmon Treaty, 1963 May 22 (Box-reel 4/2)
    Length: 25 minutes
    Description: Webster and several unidentified guests (possibly officials from the International North Pacific Commission and the International Halibut Commission) discuss the North Pacific Salmon Treaty, with an emphasis on recent revisions, such as the halibut and herring exemption clauses which will allow Japanese fisherman to harvest much closer to the Canadian coast in international waters. Issues involved include resource utilization, fish stock depletion, immature salmon catch, offshore marine fisheries, pros and cons of the treaty and its revisions, etc. Notes: film begins after 30 seconds on DVD
  - W-13 Profile of Billy James Hargis, 1963 August 23 (Box-reel 5/1)
    Sound: yes (except for first 1:45 minutes and last 2 minutes)
    Description: Webster interviews self-described militant Christian Billy James Hargis (later an ultra-conservative televangelist) during the right-wing evangelical preacher’s speaking tour of Washington State. Hargis and his organization, Christian Crusade, are devoted to denouncing communism. The first five minutes are footage of Hargis delivering his anti-communist sermon, during which he calls Khrushchev a “demon-possessed man,” and labels communism as an “international Satanic conspiracy.” Other subjects condemned by Hargis include liberalism, socialism, academic freedom, Supreme Court Justice Hugo Black, the American Black Moslem (Muslim) movement, Canadian trade with China, and rapid racial integration. Webster also grills Hargis about fundraising questions, racist remarks made by his supporters, and his support for a new invasion of Cuba to oust Fidel Castro. Hargis supports a boycott on goods produced in communist nations, such as Polish Hams. It is mentioned that the then Washington State Democratic Party Chairman (name unclear) walked out on Hargis’ sermon, calling it a “perversion of Christianity.”
  - W-14 Case of the Bogus Barrister (Raymond Burr), 1963 October 17 (Box-reel 5/2)
    Length: 27:30 minutes
    Description: Television and film actor Raymond Burr, who was born in New Westminster, B.C., is interviewed for the entire episode. He is best known for his portrayal of attorney Perry Mason in the long-running television series during the 1950s and 1960s. At the time of this interview the show had been on the air for seven years. Burr discusses plotlines, other characters, actors, and actresses. He talks about audience and fan pressure on the show to never allow Perry Mason to lose a case. Other topics include his own production company, why Hollywood is preferable to Vancouver for filming purposes, and his vacations in the Bahamas.
  - W-15 Road to Nowhere (Doukhobor story follow-up), 1963 December 12 (Box-reel 6/1)
    Film Quality (Original): mixed good / poor; requires several splices
    Description: Reel includes approximately ten minutes of interviews with Doukhobor women and disgruntled neighbors of the Doukhobor community, interspersed amongst twenty minutes of silent, fragmentary footage of the Doukhobor squatter community and daily life. The squatter community, located in a large gravel pit (town unknown), was a result of so many Doukhobor men being sent to jail two years previously (see W-4 and W-5). Reel illustrates squalid conditions of tent city, Doukhobor children at play, and hand-made crafts such as ornate wooden ladles. See also W-4, W-5, and W-26 for more Doukhobor footage.
  - W-16 William Lyon and Peter Newman Talk About McKenzie King and John Deifenbaker, 1964 January 2 (Box-reel 6/2)
    Length: 22 minutes
    Duplicate: VHS, DVD*
    Description: Webster interviews two political historians who had just written biographies about two former Canadian Prime Ministers. The first author is Peter Newman, who discusses his book about John Diefenbaker The Renegade in Power: The Diefenbaker Years. This is a highly critical account of the 1957 – 1963 reign of the progressive-conservative PM. The second is William Lyon, whose book about Mackenzie King is entitled Mackenzie King: The Lonely Heights. King served as PM three times between the 1920’s and 1948. Amongst the subjects raised about King is his alleged belief in communicating with the dead. *Note: skip the first 1:50 minutes on the DVD version
  - W-20 Berton Bares All, 1964 May 2 (Box-reel 7/1)
    Length: 21 minutes
    Description: Webster interviews noted Canadian journalist, author, and television personality Pierre Berton. Discussion centers on his earlier career in journalism, including his days at the Vancouver Sun. Berton relates anecdotes, including how he and fellow journalists released a greased pig at the press club annual ball at the Hotel Vancouver. At the time of this interview, Berton had just published his tenth book; The Big Sell. For more Pierre Berton footage see W-28.
  - W-21 The Extraordinary Equation of George Van Tassel, 1964 June 18 (Box-reel 7/2)
    Length: 24 minutes
    Duplicate: VHS, DVD, digital.
    Description: Webster interviews California resident George Van Tassel, who claims to have been visited by aliens on flying saucers that used anti-gravity technology. During the interview Van Tassel discusses the formula for time travel taught to him on a visit to a UFO, and its relationship to the Earth’s magnetic field. In later years Van Tassel would be known for the Integratron, a large dome-shaped rejuvenation device he only partially completed in the California desert prior to his death in 1978. See W-25 for a similar topic.
  - W-25 Wot! No Fingerprints, 1964 November 5 (Box-reel 8/1)
    Description: Webster interviews Dr. Frank Stranges, about alleged visitor from the planet Venus “Valiant Thor.” Stranges claims to have met the alien at the Pentagon several years previously. He also claims that Thor and 77 other Venusians travel between the Earth and Venus on UFO’s (flying saucers). Stranges cites his book, Flying Saucerama. Oddly enough, Stranges is purportedly an Evangelical Pastor from California. See W-21 for a similar topic.
  - W-26 Webster and the Cast of Characters, 1964 December 31 (Box-reel 8/2)
    Length: 27 minutes
    Film Quality (Original): Selections are fragmentary: some scenes appear to be missing. DVD blank for first 35 seconds.
    Description: New Year ’s Eve special offers memorable clips from throughout 1964, including excerpts found on W-16, W-20, W-21, and W-25. Only two excerpts are from episodes not otherwise represented in the collection. The first is from an interview with the Doukhobor spokeswoman “Big Fanny” (see W-4, W-5, and W-15) about conditions in the gravel pit squatter community and Salvation Army vouchers. The second is from an interview with a rehabilitated convict; a reformed underworld heavy who has forsaken crime and become an award-winning needlepoint artist. See W-16, W-20, W-21, and W-25
  - W-28 Uncomfortable Pew, 1965 March 4 (Box-reel 9/1)
    Description: This episode is divided into two equal parts, and features guests discussing two unrelated topics. The first in Felix Green, who discusses his book The Curtain of Ignorance and issues surrounding Canadian relations with and perceptions of communist China. Topics include Mao Tse-Tung (Mao Zedong) and the potential threat posed to the United States and Canada by China. The second is noted journalist and author Pierre Berton, who discusses his most recent and most controversial book The Comfortable Pew. Although commissioned by the Anglican Church, the book is a scathing critique of Christianity. Topics include religion, anti-religion, atheism, agnosticism, morals, and the sexual revolution. Berton puts Webster in the hot seat by skillfully exposing his hypocrisies. For more Pierre Berton footage see W-20.
  - W-29 Front Page Crisis: Vancouver Times, 1965 April 1 (Box-reel 9/2)
    Sound: yes (except first 3:40 minutes)
    Description: Webster interviews Vancouver Times executives on site as to why the startup newspaper was already suffering deep financial difficulties. Most of the episode is devoted to an interview with Mr. Val Warren (position unknown) about insolvency, advertising revenues, stockholders, subscriptions, and competition with other dailies (Warren blames an entrenched monopoly). The first 3:40 minutes are taken up by silent footage of the building, presses, and employees at work (including typesetters, editors, secretaries, receptionists, etc). The last four minutes are devoted to an interview with managing editor Brett Delaney.
  - W-30 Mohawk Princess, 1965 April 29 (Box-reel 10/1)
    Description: Native American activist Kahn-Tineta Horn is the guest for the entire episode. Model and spokeswoman for Indian rights, Horn is from the Mohawk Wolf Clan of the Kahnawake Territory in Quebec, which is part of the 6 nation Iroquois Confederacy. Horn is outspoken about treaties, education, reserves, protest strategies, and related issues. Depicted as a revolutionary by Webster, Horn is one of many activists who paved the way for Canadian legal recognition of First Nations Peoples today.
  - W-31 A Man and His Crusade (Leighton Ford), 1965 May 27 (Box-reel 10/2)
    Description: Canadian born evangelist minister Leighton Ford is interviewed for the entire episode. Ford, both a disciple and brother-in-law of Billy Graham, is known today (2005) as president of the Leighton Ford Ministries, and as honorary life chairman of the Lausanne Committee for World Evangelization. Topics include religion, spirituality, Christianity, capital punishment, executions, pacifism, socialism, church and state, and the social responsibilities of the church. Webster criticizes evangelical methods and practices.
  - W-32 This Hour has 30 Minutes (Laurier La Pierre), 1965 June 24 (Box-reel 11/1)
    Length: 29 minutes
    Description: Laurier LaPierre is the guest, and French Canadian (Quebecois) politics is the subject, for the entire episode. Topics include language issues, French Canadian cultural and political self-determination, patronage and corruption in Quebec government, potential autonomy for Quebec, and Catholic Church domination of education in the province. At the time of this broadcast, LaPierre was a well-known Canadian author, historian, journalist, and broadcaster; writer and host of the controversial CBC show This Hour Has Seven Days, and other shows such as Inquiry and Midnight. He would later serve as a Liberal Party Senator in the Jean Chrétien government, until mandatory retirement at the age of 75 in 2004. Towards the end of his life, as an openly homosexual politician, he also became an avid gay rights activist, and a founding member of the EGALE lobby for gay and lesbian rights.
  - W-33 Rebel in Kilts (Farley Mort), 1965 December 26 (Box-reel 11/2)